you could build agents that adhere to
those principles and many agents in that
set would be what we consider smart and
many of them would be stupid wait isn't
that what we have already know just yeah
right exactly so I really like what
Sherlock Holmes said that to understand
nature your mind must be as broad as
nature that's how I feel like really the
study of intelligence is that this is
brain inspired hey everyone welcome to
episode 28 of brain inspired
I am Paul Middlebrooks I had been
thinking of a way to talk about the free
energy principle on the show and I was
going to have a guest on a few weeks ago
but we had to reschedule that for a
later time but I stumbled on a recent
paper by the person you just heard Sam
Gershman who is a professor at Harvard
University and runs the computational
cognitive neuroscience lab there where
they study learning memory
decision-making
you know cognition he's recently written
about the free energy principle and how
it relates to other bigger picture
theories of how our brains function in
particular the Bayesian brain hypothesis
and the concept of predictive coding in
general so we talked about just that
during the first part of the show Sam
also co-authored a paper a couple years
ago now called building machines that
learn and think like humans the paper
breaks down some of the important
ingredients that current deep learning
networks are missing if we want to get
to human-like intelligence so we talked
about those concepts and how far along
we've come since then so those are the
two major themes during this show and of
course we discuss much more
like the limits of our own cognition and
how that affects our ability to
understand complicated processes in the
world including our own intelligence and
hang on until the end to because Sam
gives some career advice that I love for
those of you early in your career or
even deep in your career but but trying
to figure out your next course of action
your next direction every new show I do
I realize I have more and more questions
to ask of the guests to try to bring it
all together and keep you know some sort
of running thread from the previous
guests so I try to do that here but of
course I can never get to all the
questions you can find out more about
Sam and links to the stuff that we
discuss in the show notes at brain
inspired Co slash podcast slash 28 and
you can also find how to support this ad
free labor of love of a podcast but by
finding and clicking on the red patreon
button at brain inspired Co faire y'all
see May I unn and Justin did just that
this past week thank you guys that is
beautiful alright thank you for
listening the hope that your projects
are coming along smoothly and you're
immersed in and loving whatever it is
that you're pursuing
enjoy the show all right Sam Gershman
welcome and thanks for being on the show
thank you so Sam you are a you run the
computational cognitive neuroscience lab
at Harvard and you do lots of things for
instance you study how we learn you
study the different systems that we use
to learn and how they interact how our
perceptions get transformed into these
internal states in our brains and how
those states can be used to guide our
actions you study processes like
exploration versus exploitation and
plenty more today we are here to talk
about two subjects in particular one the
free
energy principle which is a hot topic
these days in in brain function and
neuroscience in your recent paper what
does the free energy principle tell us
about the brain and two we're gonna talk
a little bit about the concepts
introduced in your paper from I guess
two years ago now called building
machines that learn and think like
humans you ready mm-hmm
the free energy principle what does the
free energy principle tell us about the
brain so in this paper you compare
predictions of the free energy principle
with the Bayesian brain hypothesis and
how those two systems might fall out and
compare to each other in this realm of
what's called predictive coding now I'll
just begin by reading the opening
paragraph of a 2009 review by Carl
fistin who has been the developer of the
free energy principle just to get us
kind of rolling on this topic here so he
writes the free energy principle is a
simple postulate with complicated
implications it says that any adaptive
change in the brain will minimize free
energy this minimization could be over
evolutionary time or milliseconds in
fact the principle applies to any
biological system that resists a
tendency to disorder from single-cell
organisms to social networks I could go
on but that's his opening paragraph to
introduce the concept of the free energy
principle now I'll let you maybe comment
on this so Sam what is the free energy
principle yes so I should preface this
by saying that I'm not either an
advocate or an antagonist of the free
energy principle
I just noticed over the years that
through many conversations with
colleagues that there's widespread
confusion about what exactly the free
energy principle is and what it predicts
and so that that was the motivation for
me to enter into this fray and I should
say that the free energy principle is
closely connected to ideas that I've
proposed and have been deeply interested
in and so I think the real question here
is what
is really special about the free-energy
principle relative to other ideas that
have been out there for a while and I
can elaborate on that
so in essence the free-energy principle
is the idea that the brain minimizes
surprise mathematically it's a little
bit more complicated than that but that
really gives you the gist of it now the
term free energy is a little bit
unintuitive for a lot of people because
it actually comes from physics the idea
was that you can decompose a complicated
inference problem into inequality that
expresses the relationship between what
physicists called the partition function
and what they called the variational of
free energy and it turns out that the
object that the physicists were studying
is closely related to problems in
machine learning and statistics where
probabilistic inference problems are
intractable and they can be made more
tractable by turning them into an
optimization problem under constraints
so what does that mean and this this
actually is perhaps usefully introduced
by first talking about the Bayesian
brain hypothesis and then talking about
where the free energy principle enters
into that so the basing brain hypothesis
states that the brain is confronted with
ambiguous sensory evidence and it tries
to interpret that sensory evidence by
making inferences about the hidden
causes that produced the sensory data so
for example on our retina we get a
two-dimensional projection of a
three-dimensional world which means that
the two-dimensional information is
fundamentally ambiguous there's no
unambiguous mapping from the 2d into the
3d nonetheless we're able to perceive
three-dimensional structure in the way
we do that is we combine the noisy or
ambiguous sensory information with prior
beliefs about the nature of the world so
for example that
objects have surfaces that are smooth
and continuous
right we can exploit that those prior
beliefs to make inferences about the
hidden structure of the world and that
the Bayesian brain hypothesis is really
that the brain is using Bayes rule to
convert its prior beliefs into its
posterior beliefs the posterior beliefs
are the beliefs about hidden variables
in the world given the sensory data or
other kinds of information that the
brain has received now that sounds very
simple and if you just write down Bayes
rule it's actually mathematically
extremely simple and it's a direct
consequence of the the axioms of
probability theory the problem is that
if the space of latent variables the
hypothesis space is really large then
implementing Bayes rule computationally
is is totally intractable and part of
the algorithmic challenge is to develop
approximations of Bayes rule that can
give approximately correct answers and
that's where computer scientists and
statisticians drew inspiration from
solutions that were developed in in
physics in fact a lot of algorithmic
ideas in computer science particularly
in the domain of probabilistic reasoning
come from physics originally yeah and so
the idea was that we can convert
Bayesian inference into an optimization
problem and the way we do that is we say
that there's some family of possible
probability distributions and I'm going
to try to pick one distribution in that
family that gets as close as possible to
the true posterior distribution right a
good average to get us yeah well no it's
not necessarily a first guess it's that
I'm gonna actually try to search through
this space of distributions to find the
one that gets closest now the problem
there is that if you just state it in
that way it's just as intractable as the
original problem because you can't
compute the similarity between
distributions unless you actually know
both distributions in the whole name of
the game is that we're trying to
approximate the posterior distribution
so the way that the key algorithmic
tricked that variational inference
introduces is to put some constraints on
the family so for example if you have a
collection of hypotheses about the world
like a bunch of different dimensions of
the hypothesis space so for example
you're you're looking at you're getting
some 2-dimensional haydn you're trying
to infer both the size and the weight of
some object that you're looking at now
in general size and weight may be
correlated but you could make the
approximation that I'm only going to
consider approximations in which those
two things are uncorrelated with each
other so that that's sometimes called a
factorization of the posterior and and
it's related to what physicists called a
mean field approximation so so it turns
out that if you do that then you can you
can simplify the inference problem and
it no longer becomes intractable now
what does this all have to do with the
free-energy principle so the free energy
principle is a form of variational
inference that when we say that we're
converting an inference problem into an
optimization problem the thing that
we're optimizing is the free energy and
so so there's really no difference
between variational inference and the
free energy principle in general and in
fact there's no difference between those
things and the Bayesian brain hypothesis
in general unless you put some
constraints on the family of
distributions the this variational
family as they call it so once you start
putting constraints then the solution to
this optimization problem is no longer
identical to the true posterior okay so
that was a really nice introduction I
think to the to the topic here so but
you know you threw around a bunch of
technical terms yeah and so that your
paper is all about how you know putting
different constraints on the free energy
principle how it then matches up with
the Bayesian brain hypothesis and so on
I mean is this is this why the free
energy principle is notoriously
difficult to understand because it's a
little slippery in that it's not well to
say it's not overly constrained maybe in
an understatement because it can go so
many different ways it seems so plastic
with with the way that it can account
for different processes I mean is that
why it's so difficult to understand well
I think there's a few different factors
here so one is that you're right that
there there are a lot of degrees of
freedom depending on how you implement
the free energy principles so in in this
context as I was saying a critical
question is how do you parameterize the
distribution the family of distributions
that you're going to consider and then
also how do you search through that
space and actually solve the
optimization problem efficiently yeah so
it turns out that those different
choices have important implications
about things like predictive coding
which we can talk about but I mean
another issue here is that the papers on
free energy principle are notoriously
dense and long and hard to read and so I
think that even quite technically
literate people have trouble with that
and so I was trying to clarify some of
those issues yeah
so I mean as you were talking about the
Bayesian brain hypothesis I immediately
jumped six analogies or something and
just thought about the tabula rasa of
you know potential tabula rasa of a baby
being born let's say right and they come
out and obviously they don't have an
infinite number of distributions ready
again to then be able to parse them down
and constrain the actual problem of
sensing mom's nipple you know whatever
mm-hmm so and this actually gets to what
we may speak about later in terms of
what deep learning needs and the other
paper but it's an interesting argument
against a tabula rasa because if you
come out as a tabula rasa you do have an
overwhelming number of possibilities and
you just stuck with too many options
right of in other words your prior is
infinite so how do you even come up with
a posterior right right because how do
you choose a prior at that point so so
it's a really
it's a really intriguing and comforting
hypothesis the the and makes a lot of
sense let's say common sense to me the
way to approach how we learn and act
yeah I mean I would just try to clarify
that the free-energy principle is
somewhat different from how we choose a
prior it's certainly true that learning
about the world is impossible without a
prior there are theorems stating
basically that if you're totally
unconstrained and what you can learn
then basically you'll never be able to
generalize effectively but that's a
little bit different from the
free-energy principle which in my view
is really about algorithmic
approximations of probabilistic
inference so even after you pin down
your priors mm-hmm there's still the
question of how do you actually compute
with them how do you make inferences and
that's where all the action is in
frangie that's that's really what
differentiates free energy approaches
from just the Bayesian brain hypothesis
for it largely it's really a subset of
possible algorithmic solutions to
Bayesian inference do you want to talk a
bit about predictive coding I'm not sure
that sir I mean I don't think it's not
gonna be easy to convey the arguments
passed but none of these things are easy
really answer but but I would just make
the point that well let's start let's
start by summarizing what predictive
coding is all about so predictive coding
has been a perhaps the most influential
legacy of the free-energy principle for
Neuroscience and the idea there is that
that there are ascending and descending
or feed-forward and feedback pathways in
the brain most of the time we're talking
about cortex right and the feed-forward
pathways are conveying prediction errors
so discrepancies between observations
and expectations at each level of the
hierarchy and then the feedback pathways
are conveying those expectations let's
just contrast this with sort of a
classic view of the feed-forward
projections right
classically you could think of well not
classically I suppose I don't know what
Classic is anymore but the feed-forward
projections sort of building up a
hierarchy of representation becoming
more and more abstract would you say
that's accurate yeah yeah that's one way
to think about that it doesn't
necessarily the pretty decoding doesn't
necessarily exclude the possibility of
certain increasing level of abstraction
but it does make the strong claim which
there is some experimental evidence for
that the representation at a particular
level of the hierarchy is suppressed
that the feed-forward
pathway is suppressed if that
representation is anticipated so for
example there were studies about a
decade and a half ago using functional
MRI showing that when you present a
collection of line segments activity in
in primary visual cortex v1 is
suppressed when those those line
segments can be understood or
interpreted as a shape as incoherent
three-dimensional shape and concomitant
lis activity in the lateral occipital
complex which is known to be shape
sensitive increases so there's a
decrease in activity in v1 in an
increase of activity and LOC and that
was interpreted as arising from the this
predictive coding framework where
because the shape representation could
predict the underlying line segments
then the line segment representations
become suppressed because now they're
predictable gotcha
now what does this have to do with the
free energy principle well it turns out
that you can derive this kind of
architecture from the free energy
principle but the catch is that you have
to make a whole bunch of assumptions
that have to do it a prokta variational
family so how what space of
distributions are you going to constrain
the inference problem to you have to
make assumptions about ways in which
you're going to approximate the the free
energy itself because it turns out that
under under those chosen specify
occations you can no longer actually
analytically compute the 300 so that
anyway that the point is that there's a
bunch of ingredients that have to work
well together in order to produce
predictive coding it's not a generic
consequence of the free-energy principle
as is sometimes conveyed yes oh so this
is these are the things that you
actually explore deeper in the paper so
yeah yeah and of course the papers
online and I think it's archived right
yeah so I mean I'll link to it and
pretty soon it'll be in science I'm sure
so so Sam what do you think like the
Bayesian brain hypothesis and the free
energy principle can both be seen as
these over and these encompassing
theories of the brain function in
general right and how we aim to
understand our minds and intelligence in
general do you think that that will ever
have like a single account of our brains
and our minds well I think that the
Bayesian brain hypothesis and free
energy principle they are good
candidates for some general principles
but they're not really sufficient by
themselves right that they're too
general in some sense they're too
powerful in order to act basically you
could build agents that adhere to those
principles and many agents in that set
would be what we consider smart and many
of them would be stupid
wait isn't isn't that what we have
already know just yeah right exactly so
so but but my point is that if you want
to pin things down sufficiently that you
could say all right this kind of
architecture these kinds of constraints
these principles are only going to
produce smart things or tend to
primarily produce smart things then you
need to make more assumptions than just
that the brain is Bayesian or minimizes
surprise I mean thinking about that do
you think it's a better approach of
course both approaches together is
probably the best path but
a better approach to go to start overly
constrained or to start without enough
constraints to start with something like
the free energy principle and then and
then start whittling away with
constraints and and you know what I mean
like what approaches is a favorable
approach well there's a balance I know
yeah I mean it's important to make a
distinction between the engineering
goals of building right artificial
intelligence and the scientific goals of
trying to parse what makes humans or
animals intelligent obviously those
things will converge in some ways but
the scientific strategy is different in
the sense that we want to design
controlled experiments where we can
isolate a particular hypothesis and test
it that's different from engineering
approaches which typically aim to
construct something that does something
useful and whether or not some
particular component of it has been
isolated is not that important and
particularly in the era of building very
large deep neural network architectures
that don't have a lot of
interpretability
but can still accomplish certain kinds
of tasks that it's you know the strategy
the research strategy is different well
speaking of building things maybe we
could transition here and talk about
deep learning in the state of AI and
what it has what it needs what it's
missing so this is your paper building
machines that learn and think like
people and this is in behavioral and
brain sciences mmm-hmm and this is a
thorough paper because it's in
behavioral and brain sciences and made
even more thorough by the the format so
just I mean people know this but but
there's a target article which you guys
wrote and then there's a bunch of
reviews and then you get to rebut the
reviews and this is all in like a single
document and it costs about a three and
a half - if you really want to print the
whole thing out you know
so I've always liked that format but
I've not written one like that mm-hmm
and it's a lot of work just to get
reviews I'm one of my papers under is
under review right now and you know just
with with three to four peer reviewers
it's a lot of work just to rebut that
and send it back but it seems like a lot
more work for you guys that I mean how
did what was that experience like thing
is if it was written last year you
probably did the work twelve years ago
you know so yeah yeah no it was it was a
lot of work but it was fun to write um
you know is it it was great writing that
paper with those co-authors because it
was these were ideas that we had talked
about for a long time and it finally
forced us to really coalesce them yeah
okay sorry I had Melanie Mitchell on the
show a few weeks ago and she's a
complexity expert and she's been in the
field of AI for a long time and she had
written this op-ed in the New York Times
yeah I read that oh yeah okay so so
here's just a quote from like her
approach to this today's AI systems
sorely lack the essence of human
intelligence understanding the
situation's we experience being able to
grasp their meaning the mathematician
and philosopher Gian Carlo rota famously
asked I wonder whether or when AI will
ever crash the barrier of meaning and so
there's this phrase the barrier of
meaning and and this paper that you
co-authored takes that sort of broad
statement and breaks it down into
cognitive components that could help
bridge that gap so it's really an
initial road map of sorts and has
seemingly served as such which is pretty
must be pretty rewarding for you to have
seen so I mean maybe we can frame this
this way and maybe we can just start off
talking about how machines think and
learn currently and then maybe bring in
how humans think and learn what we know
about that and then talk about them
together so so the premise of the paper
is like
yeah we're in this we've done great work
with AI and deep learning has done
amazing things but it's still not
human-like and if we want to make it
human-like we need to build in these
other components these higher-level
components we either build them into the
deep nets or however you're going to
perform the AI build these core
ingredients in do you want to just talk
for a moment about on the current state
of how machines think yeah well it's
it's quite hard to make a really general
characterization of how machines think
because there's a hundred papers posted
on archive every day on machine learning
it's a rapidly moving target and our
paper was really focused on kind of
general patterns right so it's not the
case that our critique yeah Gaius every
machine learning paper that was ever
written but these are these are the base
that have been going on for a long time
and we discussed this history a little
bit in our paper I mean since the 70s
and 80s but by the way it's a beautiful
papal paper I really enjoyed it I bet
you I bet you've heard from a lot of
people the same as well thank you yes so
people have been going back and forth
about the necessary ingredients for
intelligence for a long time and I
sympathize with computer scientists in
some ways because there's this feeling
of moving goalposts like you're there's
a time when people said you know when a
computer can win at chess that's when we
know it's really intelligent then if it
wins I go then it's really intelligent
and it's a sort of moving goalpost and
you know I'm sure some people wonder
like when are you going to be satisfied
and I'm not really a big believer in
having a kind of single test
mm-hmm of that sort because I just think
that human telogen s-- is too
multifaceted to really be boiled down in
that way but that being said I do think
that it's important for us to think
about what we've learned from
study of cognitive science and what that
tells us about the nature of human
intelligence and the limitations of
current AI approaches so with that
premise in mind that I can kind of make
some broad stroke characterizations the
basic thrust of modern machine learning
approaches particularly deep learning
approaches has been to construct systems
that are extremely expressive in the
sense that they can learn lots and lots
of different things so we could think
about this as a kind of function
approximation problem like you get you
have a function that maps images to
object categories and that and that's
that's one way to think about an object
recognition system or you have a
translation system that's mapping text
in one language to text in another
language so these are all potentially
really complicated functions and the the
general approach has been to build very
complicated neural network architectures
now I should say they're not
conceptually complicated you can like
basically draw a picture of them and
it's pretty straightforward you have a
bunch of neurons that are connected to
each other in layers but they're
complicated in the sense that they're
very expressive they have lots of they
have lots of degrees of freedom possibly
millions of parameters that then get
optimized by a learning algorithm and so
you could you could take the same the
same Network same naive network or
whatever in training on a bunch of
different types of domains right so you
could yeah use this thing to Train it on
recognizing objects you could use this
same network to train it on language or
you know something within the real
there's a lot of possibilities yeah to
Train it yeah so it's just to maybe put
this in perspective before the heyday of
deep learning the most successful
approaches used collections of hand
engineered features so people would put
a lot of thought into defining various
kinds of image or natural language
features depending on the domain and
then they would assumed a fairly
people supervised learning algorithm
that operated on those features so for
example you might assume that there you
take it this collection of features you
map them through a linear function you
you map them through a linear classifier
and then you you basically train the
weights of that linear classifier mm-hmm
so that's a very low complexity solution
in the sense that the space of possible
functions that can be learned is very is
relatively small right so you can only
learn linear functions of this feature
set contrast that with a deep neural
network where all the different
parameters and all the layers are being
optimized to solve this classification
problem that's what's commonly called
end to end training and now you have
millions of parameters in the function
space is enormous because now you don't
necessarily you're not necessarily
restricted anymore to linear functions
you couldn't learn linear functions but
you could learn all sorts of nonlinear
functions so you might think ok well
that's great now we can learn more
functions right but that the catch is
that the more complex your function
class is the more data you need to
effectively learn it in the sense that
if you only have a small amount of data
then you could learn you could learn to
model those data very well right if you
have a very large function class you can
you can fit the training data really
well but the problem is that there may
be noise in that training data or the
train data might not be representative
sufficiently of all the test cases you
might encounter and so your your
classifier is going to fail to
generalize and and there's a whole
literature that rigorously analyzes this
from from a statistical learning
perspective it's called the study of
sample complexity how much data do you
need to effectively learn to effectively
generalize and in in general more
complex models need more data and that's
why actually the in some sense the deep
learning revolution has been just as
much about Big Data revolution in the
sense that we've constructed bigger and
bigger data sets to feed the insatiable
sample complexity needs of these
learning algorithms plus the
computational power to do so yes
absolutely and now it's the other thing
so yeah big computation is a big
contributor in some sense the deep
learning architectures we're using today
are pretty similar to the ones that we
had in the 90s but they work better
because we have a lot more data and a
lot more computing power that being said
it is still somewhat of a mystery to
learning theorists why these things work
because you know the it at first blush
the learning theories would say that you
would need even more data than we have
to effectively generalize but learning
theorists are trying to crack open that
nut and that it's probably not worth
getting into that right now but but but
the point here is that the approach
today is about building really flexible
function approximator x' now that
doesn't sound so sexy from the
perspective of artificial intelligence
to boil them down to nonlinear function
approximation but that's really what
it's all about now as I was saying the
architecture of these networks is really
flexible but it also means that that
that that very flexibility allows the
system to learn things that we might
think of as not being the right answer
hmm so it's going to pick up all sorts
of patterns but it might fail to learn
the same kinds of things that humans
learn and and they might not learn those
things in the same way so let me try to
elaborate on what I mean by that so I
was talking about complexity in terms of
the number of parameters and the size of
the function class but another way to
restrict the effective complexity of a
machine learning system is to have an
inductive bias so it says that an
inductive bias I said all right I
couldn't Theory learn any function in
this function class but I have a
preference a priori for certain
functions over others so I think that
some functions might be more plausible
than others and I can formulate that in
the language of probability theory and
that shapes the sample complexity
arguments because now even if I have a
really large function class if I have
very strong inductive biases that can
kind of compensate for the four
the need to experience a lot of data
that inductive biases basically say that
some things are going to be easier to
learn with less data and other things
are going to be harder to learn and will
require more data and is that how does
that compare to having a stronger priors
those are rights right so inductive bias
these are priors when you can you can
construct depending on what you're
you're kind of formal framework is you
can talk about inductive biases in a in
a non Bayesian way but I often think
it's helpful to think about prior
distributions as a particular way of
representing inductive bias if I say
okay so so now so let me try to loop
this back to human cognition we think
that humans can learn from small amounts
of data precisely because they have very
strong inductive biases hmm and they
also have inductive biases that are
relatively abstract which allows them to
generalize their knowledge very widely
so let me just talk about some of those
inductive biases actually let before
before I talk about inductive biases let
me just try to make vivid why you need
an inductive bias at all there's a great
book by Eric Baum called what is thought
and he has the following example so
imagine I'm training a chair classifier
so I'm giving it images and it's telling
me chair or not chair all right so I
give it some finite number of these
training images and it learns to
perfectly classify to perfectly
discriminate chairs from non chairs all
right now I'm going to give it a new
chair and I wanted to generalize to that
now let's imagine that it had no
inductive bias okay
the implication of having no inductive
bias is that in fact this classifier
which could perfectly discriminate
between chairs and non chairs in the
training set has no basis of
generalizing to this new image that in
fact it will be completely uncertain
about it would have no basis of knowing
whether this new image is a chair or non
chair and the reason is because in a
continuous function
space there are an infinite number of
functions that separate the chairs from
the non chairs and that means that
there's an infinite number of functions
that would perfectly separate chairs
from non chairs and and classify this
new image as a chair and then there's
also an infinite number of functions
that perfectly separate chairs from non
chairs and classify this new image as a
non chair okay and what it means to have
no inductive bias is that you have no
preference about which of those
functions is the correct function so
generalization depends crucially on
having some inductive bias now neural
networks do have inductive biases
the architecture of the network the
parameterization and so on those are all
at forms of inductive biases but they're
just relatively weak inductive bias
right now we think that humans have
strong inductive biases they haven't
strong inductive biases about things
like causality about objects about
relations between objects about
compositionality of knowledge so that
the idea that you can build complex
representations out of simpler ones and
we have strong inductive biases about I
in different domains that take the forms
of something like an intuitive theory
like an intuitive theory of psychology
that lets us make inferences about other
people's minds or an intuitive theory of
physics that allows us to make
inferences about physical interactions
in the world
anyway I'll stop there and let you look
well no that's that's okay because
you're sort of rattling off the the
ingredients that are proposed in this in
this paper so and you just got there
naturally which is a you know a
beautiful thing yeah so so I was gonna
ask about how humans learn right and in
in comparison which is where you've
really just brought us to anyway but
before we even get into just a few maybe
of the examples of these things that you
just listed it's an interesting
conundrum whether we understand how
humans learn well enough to then so the
whole goal is to build systems that
learn and think like humans but do we
learn do we know how humans learn and
think well enough to even begin doing
that and so these are things you know
like when you say terms like intuitive
physics oh of course
well let's just maybe even put that
question on hold unless you want to
answer it
and then we can kind of step through a
few of the ingredients well no I I mean
I don't think that we know enough about
human cognition that we can just
implement human intelligence in a
computational system it's more just that
we have some general hints and also some
specific computational models about how
humans think and those are in
interesting ways different from a lot of
the prevailing deep learning
architectures now I will say that even
at the time that we were writing that
behavioral and brain sciences article
people were already starting to realize
this so for example in the domain of
intuitive physics there was a lot of
interest in building machine learning
systems that that solved intuitive
physics problems and if you build them
in a kind of naive sort of off-the-shelf
way they didn't work very well
right and they only started to work
really well when people started building
in constraints and and I would argue
that those a lot of the constraints that
worked well were precisely the
constraints that we think people have so
for example deepmind and other groups
have developed models in which there are
primitives that correspond to objects
and there are functional interactions
between the objects so it's a relational
model that's object-oriented and then
you use deep learning to learn the
parameters of those functional
interactions and that works much better
for for modeling intuitive physics so I
would argue that that's kind of
harnessing the strengths of deep
learning which are really about flexible
function approximation with the kinds of
inductive biases that we think humans
have okay so let's just step through
these so there are five core ingredients
is that the latest count I mean this is
the sort of the count in the in the
paper huh yeah so so one of them is this
intuitive physics that you're just
talking about and this is the idea of so
so this falls under the rubric of when
we're really young we're kind of born
with and have really early on this
developmental software right so that's
sort of ingrained
or an inductive bias right so so
intuitive physics is the idea that we
understand that
one cue ball hits when one pool ball
hits the other billiard ball we
understand that there's a collision
there these two things are solid and one
affects the other yeah well it's a lot
more than that probably but well yeah
that's one aspect of it yeah that's one
aspect of it so you know the things are
solid not illiquid and and yeah and so
on and so on so so this is one thing
that is sort of missing in deep learning
networks that you were just describing
that's and there's being there's work
being done on all of this like I said
it's uh it's this is the nice roadmap
that people have seemingly been
following actually so another one of
those that falls under the rubric of
developmental software is the intuitive
psychology like you were just that you
that you mentioned do you wanna just
describe what that is briefly yeah so so
maybe just first for those people who
are not familiar with the notion of an
intuitive theory the reason that they're
called intuitive theories is to contrast
them with scientific theories yeah and
the argument is that intuitive theories
and scientific theories shared a lot of
the same structural characteristics but
obviously they differ in content in the
sense that you know intuitive psychology
doesn't have access to you know
functional MRI and response time studies
and so on right but but we still can
build a theory like representation of
another person's mind for example we can
reason about another person's beliefs
and desires and combine our beliefs our
knowledge of those beliefs and desires
to for example make predictions about
what that person is going to do mm-hmm
another example would be you know when
kids are shown kids can discriminate
between whether an acting agent is is
helping another agent or hindering the
other agent and so the yeah there are
these psychological aspects of other
agents that can easily be inferred with
this sort of developmental startup
software yeah okay and then the rest of
the other three ingredients kind of fall
under what you describe as model
building elements and one of them is
this company and you've listed all these
already if you've mentioned these in
passing so one is cop isn't
compositionality mm-hm and this is
basically where you can build new things
from simpler parts mm-hmm and so deep
networks and let's just run through
these real quick and then we can kind of
talk about them more broadly maybe the
deep networks are not great at this
another is learning to learn or meta
learning and so there's actually a lot
to talk about with this probably and and
causality is the last the fifth
ingredient and building causality and I
talked about this last episode a little
bit with Conrad hurting and you want a
modern ESCO his wife because they just
wrote a paper on how to infer causality
in quasi-experiments
so it's a little bit different okay so
like I said this has been a road map and
it's like the paper was written and then
learned meta-learning work immediately
came out of deep mind and then I don't
know if you recently I didn't get a
chance to read the paper but there's
this recent paper out of deep mind as
well that is using the meta
reinforcement there meta reinforcement
learning framework to build in causality
tool it was written by my student oh is
that right well I should have internship
that at deep mind okay very good yes
it's funny because in the paper and one
of the rebuttals from the people at deep
mind they're like maybe we are on a
converging path here and so I suppose
you are I know we're definitely there's
definitely points of convergence there
not not completely but I mean I talked
to those people on a regular basis so
it's not we're not like you know in
conflict or anything oh of course not
we're all in going for the same goal
anyway yeah so so I don't know if you
want to if any of those that you want to
really elaborate on as something that
you know I'm kind of curious your take
on how the paper has continued to be
received over time and and how people
you know if you've seen a lot of
progress in all of these domains or
what's really still lacking etc yeah I
think I think that there's been a ton of
progress I think that as I was saying
before many people have begun to
acknowledge that you need to build in
some constraints to get these systems to
work appropriately now we're certainly
not there yet in a lot of practical
areas of application you know for
example we we still
I think can't get systems to make
reasonable captions for images it's just
the fact of matters they just don't
really understand what's going on in the
image the barrier of meeting but they
make reasonable captions you know five
out of seven times maybe now is that a
good I don't know I mean nice okay yeah
yeah anyway but the point is just that
these systems can sometimes fool us into
thinking that they know more than they
really do and yeah so so I'm encouraged
by things like the paper you mentioned
meta learning for causal inference I
think that those kinds of approaches are
definitely on the right track I don't
know to what extent the particular
basically the thing that I wonder about
is to what extent building exploring in
the space of kind of different neural
network contraptions putting in
different kinds of widgets and so on is
going to get us to intelligence and
sometimes it feels a little bit like
building a ladder to the moon doing more
the same that didn't get us there
initially and yeah well it's just it's
just I mean certainly there's no doubt
that there's been a huge amount of
progress but it also you I get the sense
reading these papers that we're kind of
swirling around a local optimum and
every once in a while we kind of pop out
of that and go a little bit farther but
the developments don't seem of the sort
that are really getting a significantly
closer to human intelligence so I it's
just um to give one example I think
about alphago you know alphago is an
amazing accomplishment look I love and
everyone has to always preface it with
how amazing it is and there yeah yeah
yeah well it's an amazing accomplishment
there's no doubt about that but just
think about what happens at the end of a
go game you shut it down because público
can only play go and that's in some
sense true of almost all the models that
we have now and even even with
the space of let's say video games so we
have algorithms that can play video
games but you can make changes to those
games that would be completely trivial
to a human player and yet would be
catastrophic to these algorithms yeah so
we're really far away I think in the
sense of capturing that human-like
flexibility and I and I think it's
because we haven't fully embraced the
principles of causality and
compositionality and intuitive theories
and so on I think I think I guess my
general impression is that we have this
really useful tool that we can build
these gadgets out of neural networks
that do things and you if you can feed
it and updater they can you know
classify images or recognize speech but
it's tempting to kind of over apply
those things as a substitute for really
thinking hard about the structure of a
problem but it'd be fair to say that
that it's a sort of a change in quantity
when you're adding these sorts of
widgets etc to the deep learning
networks and not quality yeah yeah I
think that most of the advances that we
see on a day to day basis are about like
you know getting a few more decimal
points score on some benchmark data set
but you're not really you I think the
real contribution of cognitive science
is to get people out of the thinking in
terms of get people move people away
from thinking in terms of these
benchmarks and and or rather thinking
about thinking more broadly about what
the benchmarks really are what what is
it that you want the system to do it's
not a just about playing go or playing
video games or recognizing objects
there's some set of competences there
that transcend those individual tasks
and if you only kind of play to win
those tasks then you're going to be
missing something so we need to figure
out where the hell we actually want the
goal posts and pour concrete and then
make them stick there huh yeah yeah yeah
so I asked this to a lot of my guests so
I'll ask you as well is emulating the
human mind is that you know is emulating
human thought and learning is that the
only way to get there you think too
to general AI to something that we would
satisfy that would satisfy our notion of
what generally is well can I tell you
what you're gonna say before you say it
yeah go for it
you're gonna say well it's the only
example that we have it's the best
example it's the most complicated you
know the brains most complicated thing
in the universe okay now go ahead and
repeat what I said and I'll be saying I
think it depends on what you mean by
general intelligence because it could
potentially be a tautology if we think
that what we mean by general
intelligence is whatever we think humans
do then that's only going to be
satisfied when we build machines that
think like humans but we might not right
maybe we'll eventually come to some way
of thinking about intelligence that's
really different from our own it's just
it's very hard to get to that point
because inevitably we project our own
notions of intelligence onto our
machines of course but I mean one way to
approach this potentially is from you
know the computational level so we can
always talk about David Marr and the
conformational highest in level and
where where would you start like the
free energy principle for instance I
think starts with existence itself right
as the you know the fact that we exist
and if you start in that level well then
what's the for living things and what's
the algorithm maybe that's is that
evolution and you know I don't know is
there is there a way to come at it from
a really high computational level where
then the algorithms could differ or you
know for instance and then the
implementation level below that could
differ as well to get to that same
whatever the actual computational level
is of living in existence
this is getting a little too deep I'm
sure for the for the podcast but well we
I think that's absolutely right I mean
there's some sense in which like at the
very highest level it's to like do well
at life right just survive and reproduce
the imperatives of natural selection and
so on but that as we talked about before
is not very constraining on theories of
intelligence at least in its most
general form yes
so we need to make more specific
assumptions but but just to make this a
little bit more concrete so even if I
said all right an intelligent system has
to reason according to Bayes rule then
there's they're going to be algorithmic
constraints to grapple with in
intractability of that in any large
domain and it's perfectly conceivable
that a machine we could design machine
learning algorithms that Excel whatever
algorithms humans are using because
there's no reason to think that
evolution is necessarily selected the
best possible algorithm to solve these
problems there is no best best is just
what is existing at the time I suppose
right right why I mean yes so I'm saying
within whatever particular niche you're
looking at you could ask like what is
the best way to solve this problem and
humans might not have achieved that so
for example people might engage in some
kind of tree search to solve planning
problems or they might engage in some
kind of like variational optimization to
solve inference problems but the
particular way in which they do that
might not actually be the optimal way
and we could we could design machine
learning algorithms that do better than
humans now they're still trying to their
design to achieve the same goals that
humans want to achieve and that the
overarching architecture of that system
is similar but it's doing it differently
right so that's that's a concrete way in
which it wouldn't even make sense at
that point to demand that the machines
adhere slavishly to it would make no
sense what humans are doing right yeah
yeah so I I mean I the reason you know I
told you what you're going to say I mean
I was a joke obviously but yeah so many
people have said that you know they
can't imagine another way and my
intuition is that wow you know if you
ask a hundred experts and they all say
no way we have to do it this way it must
be the other way you know you know I
can't I can't imagine another way but I
can imagine right there being another
way in the same way that I was very
struck by I think this has very deep
implications for how we think about
ourselves and our own thought process so
I
attended a dinner once and I talked to
this geologist who was working on
earthquake prediction and he made the
very vociferous point that he felt that
the classical education and geology had
ruined generations of geologists come
because the classical models simply
could not accurately predict earthquakes
like tectonic plate shift models or this
is what he said I'm not a demain
occurred and he didn't really go into
the details of why that was yeah yeah
that you could have sound geophysical
principles that were not actually useful
at making predictions and he argued that
this whole thing was blow and wide open
when people started to use deep learning
to predict earthquakes and he felt that
whatever it is that we thought we knew
about geology you know even if it was
right maybe there are more correct
theories of geology that are expressed
in some inscrutable language that the
deep learning system can discover yeah
and eludes us and I I have a hard time
swallowing that but at the same time you
know you have to acknowledge the
possibility that it's our hubris as
humans that convinces us that the the
nature of the universe has to be
expressible in the language that that we
have at our disposal right now in the
scientific language in current use I
mean this was this is something that
historians of science have known for a
long time that our theories are strongly
latched to our description languages and
even our basic observations can't be
described in the theory independent way
when our theories change our
observations change we actually see
things differently and so so that's
reason for humility in terms of
privilege in our notions of intelligence
right right well in that same vein I had
John Krakauer on the show a few weeks
ago and and we were talking about
different levels of explanation and you
know we talked about reductionism and in
the proper level of understanding
phenomena and there are lots of like
high
cognitive functions that it may not make
sense to try to understand on the level
of neurons and neural circuits right but
instead on the level of some behavioral
function and and so on and the like the
core ingredients that you guys mentioned
in your paper confer like these
advantages right they make humans so
awesome in various ways and I'm
wondering you know could there be
disadvantages too and they'll have to be
right that that's the yin and yang is
the trade I yeah so that's what I was
thinking too is like you know let's say
it is possible you know we can map some
of these these higher level cognitive
functions to the level of neural
circuits you know are we humans but you
know because we need to reduce
complexity using things like
compositionality and and intuitive
physics are we incapable of conceiving
how that mapping could occur whereas
like a deep learning network or some
sort of AI system without these
human-like skills quote-unquote or
limits might by brute force figure it
out in a way that we could eventually be
satisfied with that kind of explanation
you know does that does that make sense
yeah I so i wouldn't say that people are
incapable of doing this since
historically we've been very capable of
constructing various kinds of cognitive
prosthesis that allow us to understand
things that seemed mystifying before
that being said it's certainly a logical
possibility that neural networks could
discover these theories maybe more
easily than us because they have
different inductive biases than us I
certainly think it's within the realm of
possibility to think about neural
network scientists that are as different
from us as we are from you know dogs and
cats now not as but but that being said
I think my experience in studying these
systems is that in some sense there's
always less than meets the eye that like
that we have this strong inclination to
kind of anthropomorphize these systems
and attribute to them
psychological competences that they lack
and when you start to really test these
rigorously they fall short I mean this
is very clear in the domain
for example of natural language where
most natural language processing systems
simply don't recover the same kind of
semantic understanding of the world that
humans have it's not that hard to
demonstrate this so so I just think that
while it's a logical possibility I think
we need to be doing more than just
training neural networks on imagenet
before like you know data set they eat
even data sets on reasoning from natural
language I think are too impoverished
but see isn't it it's a it's really a
privilege to be able to be at the point
where we can say that and you know that
there have been these advances right
that are amazing now we can say it's not
enough that's great I think that's a
place to be in mmm-hmm so I can imagine
like lots of different scenarios for
this path toward puzzly what we would
could call general AI and reading your
paper brought just one to me is this one
scenario and as soon as you write this
in a science fiction book it means it's
gonna be completely wrong but so you
know I can imagine and you know the way
I the way I sort of envision it is what
we're building toward is an AI system
that comes off the shelf out of the box
and it's ready to solve new problems and
learn new things efficiently and and and
have some of these built-in ingredients
right that that are proposed in the
paper mm-hmm I can also imagine a
scenario though where we the service and
in between phase where we have to build
these machines that then we set out into
the world like with little embodied
cognitive architectures and then we have
to wait for them to gather enough
different kinds of data and experience
that we can't build into them mm-hmm you
know do you think that's a possibility
that will go through this phase where
we're you know taking these these BOTS
these robots and stuff and then letting
them be for a while and then we can use
them for instance then then their
general domain general enough that we
can actually use them or you know can
you imagine that kind of scenario it's a
ridiculous question okay yeah I mean I
don't see why not although of course
there's all sorts of ethical and
practical issues sure that loose robots
in the world in depends what kind of
constraints we put on them and
what kind of challenges you know do they
have to enter the workforce and work for
there oh definitely
definitely yes for me anyway yeah so I
came up through neurophysiology in my my
graduate work and my postdoctoral work
and this podcast I made has the tagline
we're neuroscience and AI converge but I
always have thought of and and I'm only
starting to not think of it this way
I've always thought of cognitive science
as a part of neuroscience now that
neuroscience sort of subsumes psychology
even you know mm-hmm it seems to depend
on whose definition you like of these
things but so this paper was written in
a real from a real cognitive science
historical perspective and modern-day
sense of of cognitive science do you
think that we're in a cognitive science
resurgence sort of over over
neuroscience so there was a lot of hype
in neuroscience right we're gonna figure
all this out and now cognate is
cognitive science coming back now and
saying whoa whoa you know this is the
way to go are we in this resurgence to
understand how how to understand the
brain and how to programme machines that
think like brains it depends who you ask
I mean there's certainly still people
who argue very strenuously that
neuroscience is really important for
building intelligent machines I just I
don't think either for cognitive science
or for neuroscience you know psychology
or neuroscience they're both in some
sense very dependent on our
computational notions we need ideas from
machine learning and other disciplines
technical formal ideas to interpret both
psychological and neural data I don't
think it's the case that we've gotten a
lot of mileage out of just looking at
those data and from that extracting
algorithms that we can plug into machine
learning systems I just don't think
that's how it really works
people have different arguments about
this of course yeah so let's kind of
transition I just have a few general
kind of broad questions for you and then
we'll then I'll let you go okay
I will see how you perform on this one
so in the spirit of human compositional
skills and and our ability to produce
infinite things from a finite set of
things mm-hmm can you say I'm uh Turei
grammatically correct English sentence
right now that you think nobody has ever
said or written sure yeah I don't think
that is I mean you could do any variant
of Chomsky's classic sentence colorless
green ideas sleep furiously you could
have them sleep quiet sleep
professionally effervescent Li yeah
colorfully they dead verbs it's the
adverbs that allow them to do this yeah
yeah I think it's pretty straightforward
to do that okay um I could you know I
could say the sentence I don't believe
that Chomsky said that colorless green
ideas sleep furiously I bet that's been
said but we'll see Oh someone can google
it okay so often when we're stuck and
need to figure out the solution to some
sort of problem we need to step away
from the problem right you can't just
like you know you're at your desk you're
trying to figure this thing out but it's
only later when you step away that you
know the solution comes to you and often
like immersing ourselves in a like
long-form complicated novel for instance
can lead to more creative ideas than
like reading a summary of that novel
right presumably because we need to sort
of steep in that mind frame for longer
not the things bubble in or in our minds
do you think that there is something
about time scales in this I thought you
might be going to this when you're
talking about your dinner with the with
the geologist is there something about
time scales and dynamics and processing
time that is important for how we think
and learn and how maybe machines might
need to think and learn so so thinking
of you know the idea is can like the the
the geo geological formations right
they're moving and they're they're a
dynamical system could we if you stepped
back
on a really slow timescale with those
look intelligent could we make the case
that those looked intelligent right or
is there something special about the
millisecond processing times of our
brain that gives rise to intelligence
and that we need to consider when
building machines I don't think so I
mean it's not entirely clear whether you
mean that the time skills refer here to
the time skills of computational
processing versus the time scales of
events unfolding in our world I could
clearly we can reason about events that
happen on it vastly different time
scales even though the time scale of our
neural processing is fixed I didn't say
they're gonna be good questions
yeah constraint yeah I mean I think that
there's something important about time
scale but I'm not sure what it is I mean
it is an intriguing question why
thinking over long periods of time would
help you what what is a one idea that
you seemingly you have time to do all
your ideas but what's one idea that you
either you know don't have the resources
or time to tackle that you wish someone
else might pursue yeah well a lot of my
questions about the brain really need to
be answered in animal models and
although I do human experiments in my
lab I don't do animal experiments and so
typically I try to farm out those animal
experiments to other labs that do that
kind of research and that's been no no
pun intended yeah that's been very
fruitful for me to answer questions for
example about the nature of dopamine
processing so there's lots of questions
like that I mean often the kinds of
experiments that we do we we often try
to design them in such a way that both
humans and animals could do those tasks
and then eventually eventually try to
port them over to animals and there's
some yeah you know process of convincing
an animal experimentalist to take on
that challenge well they're busy you
know other things going on well it's not
just they're busy I think they're also
they're conservative understandably
because it takes a long time as you know
to Train animal that's what I mean
they're busy yeah steeped in their
two-year other other experiment if you
could bet on a single discipline or sub
discipline that will that will break
open our understanding of the human mind
what would it be you could say cognitive
science physics astrology etc well I
feel like the longer that I do this
stuff it just seems that the more
everything kind of converges that we
already talked about how physicists came
up with this idea of free energy that
then got picked up by computer
scientists to develop efficient
inference algorithms that then got
picked up by neuroscientists to think
about the brain yeah I mean these all
all these things are intertwined they're
they're deep both formal and
metaphorical relationships between all
these concepts and so I really like what
Sherlock Holmes said that to understand
nature your mind must be as broad as
nature that's how I feel like really the
study of intelligence is that in a
nutshell right you need the intelligence
is drawing upon all of these different
disciplines and ways of thinking so in
that vein keeping one's mind as broad as
possible do you have a advice that you
would give to you know say a graduate
student or an undergraduate interested
in these topics and just wanting to
start out in the arena like what how to
how to move forward yeah I think it's
hard for students to follow the path of
greater resistance because they look
around and they see what's happening
what's successful what's not successful
and it's natural for people to gravitate
towards the things that they perceive as
being more successful but the paradox is
that to be really successful to really
make a difference to change the way
people are thinking to change the course
of scientific discovery you have to swim
against the current you have to pursue
ideas that are not popular that
people might not agree with that but
that might not really make sense at
first you have to befriend crackpots and
read poetry and you know take long walks
and do all the things that aren't
ostensibly the right things to do the
productive things the good uses of time
right so so we have to be really
attentive to the unappreciated
importance of uselessness well that's a
good quote i tempted in there but I'll I
have one more question for you here so
yeah well AI help us understand
consciousness what it is how it works
etc yeah I'm not sure should it ended
with the last one I I don't feel like I
can really give a good answer to that
because to me most of the things that we
do that are intelligent are not
necessarily conscious or what what's the
conscious part of them is just kind of
the surface the perceptible surface but
most of the interesting computation is
going on under the hood and that's why
the study of psychology has moved away
from just asking people what they're
thinking is demonstrably people don't
really know what they're thinking
mm-hmm so in my view consciousness is a
little overrated damn alright well I
know what I'm thinking I'm feeling
grateful and thinking I'm glad to have
you on the show so Sam where where
should people go to learn more about you
well they can look at my lab web page
and if they're interested in reading my
papers that's where they all are very
good that'll also be linked to in the
show notes so so thanks for your time
Sam and continued good luck to you yeah
thanks so much Paul take care brain
inspired is a production of me you can
support the show through patreon for a
trifling 2 or 4 dollars per month go to
patreon.com/scishow and inspired co
find the red patreon button there your
contribution will help keep this show
going without any annoying
advertisements like you hear on other
shows to get in touch with me email Paul
at brain inspired Co the music you hear
is by the new year find them at the new
year net thank you for your support see
you next time
[Music]